Pola Nirenska Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Correspondence, 1934-1992 (Box 1-3)
  - Prevots, Naima, 1968 [?] (1 item) (Box-folder 2/58)
  - "P" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/59)
  - "Q" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/60)
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1987 (1 item) (Box-folder 2/61)
  - "R" miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/62)
  - Sande, Rona, 1968, 1991, n.d. (9 items) (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Sande, Stuart A., n.d. (1 item) (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Seidl, Ina, 1935, 1949, n.d. (3 items). Letter dated 1949 is signed "R. S." (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Shurr, Gertrude, 1987-92 (6 items) (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Simmons, Stephanie [?], n.d. (1 item) (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Sorell, Walter, 1951, 1987, 1992 (4 items) (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Spelman, Marva, 1991 (5 items) (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Sprague, Judy [?], 1967 (1 item) (Box-folder 3/8)
  - "S" miscellaneous (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Thimey, Erika, 1963, n.d. (3 items) (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Tievsky, Jan, 1991 (1 item) (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Tour, Evelyn de la [and others], 1953 (1 item) (Box-folder 3/12)
  - "T" miscellaneous (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Union of Polish Stage Artists Abroad, 1949 (1 item) (Box-folder 3/14)
  - "U" miscellaneous (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Veen, Jan, n.d. (1 item) (Box-folder 3/16)
  - "V" miscellaneous (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Weber, Reinhard, 1948-49 (4 items) (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Wigman, Mary, 1935-48 (3 items) (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Wyrrick, Sharon, 1987, n.d. (3 items) (Box-folder 3/20)
  - "W" miscellaneous (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Young Men's and Young Women's Hebrew Association Educational Department, 1954 (1 item) (Box-folder 3/22)
  - "Y" miscellaneous (Box-folder 3/23)
  - "Z" miscellaneous (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Unidentified (Box-folder 3/25)
- Choreographic Notes (Box 4)
  The Choreographic Notes series consists of notes from works choreographed in the United States.
  Arranged alphabetically by title
  - American folk suite, "If I had a ribbon". Received in audio recording tape box (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Departures. Received in audio recording tape box (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Double concerto in d minor [?] (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Exits. One page received in audio recording tape box (Box-folder 4/4)
  - The four horsemen of the apocalypse (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Russia: the transparent apple and the silver saucer, "Snow in Siberia" solo choreographed for Liz Lerman (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Shakespearean suite (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Strange visit (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Studio work (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Tired magician (Box-folder 4/10)
  - The train (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Vivaldi. Received in audio recording tape box (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Unidentified (Box-folder 4/13)
- Programs, 1933-1990 (Box-folder 5/1-3)
  The Programs series is represented by two subseries: Performances by Nirenska and Performances by others. Performances by Nirenska consist of printed and typescript programs from 1933-90; all of the programs are not included in this series; more programs can be found in the scrapbooks and subject files, and additional information may be obtained in personal papers, addresses, and cards. Performances by others consists of printed and typescript programs saved by Nirenska from 1931-88.
  - Performances by Nirenska (Box-folder 5/1-2)
    - 1933-68 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - 1980-90 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Performances by Others (Box-folder 5/3)
    - 1931-88 (Box-folder 5/3)
- Publicity, 1927-1992 (Box-folder 5/4-7)
  The Publicity series is represented by two subseries: About Nirenska and About others. About Nirenska consists of printed and typescript publicity materials such as flyers and posters, from 1933-90; more materials can be found in the scrapbooks and subject files. About others consists of printed and typescript publicity materials such as flyers and posters, from 1927-92 (and undated).
  - About Nirenska (Box-folder 5/4)
    - 1933-90 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - About Others (Box-folder 5/5-7)
    - 1927-90 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - 1991-1992, n.d. (Box-folder 5/6-7)
- Scrapbooks, 1933-1992 (Box 6-11)
  The Scrapbooks series consists of thirteen scrapbooks containing photographs, clippings, articles, programs, publicity materials, and correspondence.
  Arranged chronologically
  - [No. 1] Photographs, portraits, and sculptures, 1933-60s (Box-folder 6/1-2)
  - [No. 2] United States, Poland, Austria, England, and Italy, 1933-45 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - [No. 3] England and Israel, 1946-47 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - [No. 4] England, Austria, and Switzerland, 1947-49 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - [No. 5] United States, 1949-50 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - [No. 6] United States, 1951-57 (Box-folder 8/2-3)
  - [No. 7] United States, 1958-59 (Box-folder 8/4-5)
  - [No. 8] United States -- her own school, 1960-65 (Box-folder 9/1-2)
  - [No. 9] United States, Turkey, Greece, and Lebanon, 1965-67 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - [No. 10] Photographic interlude, 1967-80 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - [No. 11] United States, 1981-84 (Box-folder 10/2-3)
  - [No. 12] 1985-92 (Box-folder 11/1-2)
  - [No. 13] Miscellaneous photographs, clippings, and publicity materials (Box-folder 11/3)
- Photographic Materials, 1930s-1992 (Box 12-21, Box 28-30)
  The Photographic Materials series is represented by three main subseries: Photoprints, Negatives, and Slides by Nirenska. The Photoprints subseries (all b&w and 8 x 10 in. or less in size unless noted otherwise) is divided into a number of subseries. The material consists of the following: publicity and informal shots, solo works performed by Nirenska; publicity and informal shots, works by Nirenska with her included as a performer; publicity shots and informal portraits, works by Nirenska without her performing. The Negatives subseries is divided into a number of subseries. The material consits of the following: publicity shots of her works, 8 x 10 copy negatives; arranged alphabetically by title of work; in works by Nirenska and informal portraits, all b&w and 35 mm. in size unless noted otherwise; arranged alphabetically by name or title of work. The Slides by Nirenska subseries consists of color slides by Nirenska.
  Various arrangements are applied
  - Photoprints (Box 12-18, Box 28-30)
    - Nirenska alone (Box 12-13, Box 28)
      - 1930s (Box-folder 12/1)
      - The cry [?], 1930s (Box-folder 12/2)
      - 1933. By Zofja Kruzówna (Box-folder 12/3)
      - 1933. By Zygmunt Szajer (Box-folder 12/4)
      - 1936 (Box-folder 12/5)
      - Polish dance, 14-1/2 x 11-1/2, 1937. By Landseer, London; autographed (Box-folder 29/1)
      - Modeling in London. By Landseer, London (Box-folder 12/6)
      - Angel of death. By Gerti Deutsch, Vienna (Box-folder 12/7)
      - Eastern ballad, 11-3/4 x 8-3/4, 12 x 9-1/4, 12 x 9-1/2. By John Deakin; autographed (Box-folder 12/8, 28/1)
      - Felina -- catty woman, 11-3/4 x 10, 9-3/4 x 11-1/2. By John Deakin; autographed (Box-folder 12/9, 28/2)
      - La puerta del vino, 10-3/4 x 10, 11 x 10. By John Deakin (Box-folder 12/10, 28/3)
      - A scarecrow remembers, 11-3/4 x 8-3/4, 12 x 9-3/4. By John Deakin; autographed (Box-folder 12/11, 28/4)
      - Unwanted child, 12 x 10, 10-1/2 x 9-1/2. By John Deakin; autographed (Box-folder 12/12, 28/5)
      - Modeling, four 12 x 10, three 11 x 8-1/4, 11 x 8-1/2 (Box-folder 12/13, 28/6)
      - Posing in a mirror (Box-folder 12/14)
      - 10 x 10 (Box-folder 28/7)
      - 1956 [?]. By Angus McBean; autographed (Box-folder 12/15)
      - 1960s. By B. Vern Blasdell, Washington, DC (Box-folder 12/16-19)
      - 1960 Jan. (Box-folder 12/20)
      - 13-1/2 x 10-1/2 (Box-folder 28/8)
      - By Terry Walker (Box-folder 13/1)
      - In studio, 1980s, color and b&w. By Ray C. Schandelmeier, b&w photographs from "Portraits of a friend" (Box-folder 13/2)
      - 1980s. By Ray C. Schandelmeier from "Portraits of a friend" (Box-folder 13/3)
      - Unidentified, color and b&w (Box-folder 13/4)
    - Nirenska with others (Box 13, Box 16, Box-folder 28/9, Box-folder 30/1)
      - Mary Wigman Schule, 1930s. By Kastan, Hamburg (Box-folder 13/5)
      - Percussion ensemble, 1930s. By Atelier Robertson, Berlin (Box-folder 13/6)
      - With Mary Wigman, 1948. By Hans Tschirren (Box-folder 13/7)
      - Congress of International Dance at Zurich, 1949. By Hans Tschirren; Hilda Baumann, Mary Wigman, and Nirenska in front (Box-folder 13/8)
      - With Madame Maria Hershman-Horch, Director of Berkshire Drama School, 1950 Aug. By E. H. Aoole [?] (Box-folder 13/9)
      - With Evelyn de la Tour and Lucia L., Hains Point, 1952 (Box-folder 13/10)
      - 1959 Dec. (Box-folder 16/1)
      - Departures: Dorothy Madden, Nicole Pearson, Rona Sande, Nirenska, and Beth Osgood Chanock, 11 x 14, 1959 (Box-folder 28/9)
      - American folk suite, "The three sisters: Rona Sande, Nicole Pearson, and Nirenska (Box-folder 13/11)
      - Shakespearean suite, 1961 Nov. 28. By Naltchayan; Nicole Pearson as Kate in Taming of the shrew, Beth Osgood Chanock as Portia, and Nirenska as Lady Macbeth (Box-folder 13/12)
      - Dance class, 1960 Oct. 6. By Naltchayan (Box-folder 13/13)
      - Ballet class, 1960s. By Fred Ward, Arlington, Virginia; print and contact sheets (Box-folder 13/14)
      - Session with dance teachers in Beirut, 1967 Jan. By David (Box-folder 13/15)
      - Panel discussion with Hanya Holm, Erika Thimey, Nirenska, and Sali Ann Kriegsman, 1986. Dancefest '86, celebrating national dance week, Glen Echo Park, MD; May 3-5 (Box-folder 16/2-80)
      - With Ethyl Butler. By G. Vern Blasdell, Washington, DC (Box-folder 13/16)
      - With Jan Karski, 1987 June, 1991 (Box-folder 13/17)
      - With Nancy Schandelmeier, 1990s. By Ray C. Schandelmeier from "Portraits of a friend" (Box-folder 13/18)
      - Schandelmeier wedding. By Ray C. Schandelmeier from "Portraits of a friend" (Box-folder 13/19)
      - With Laura Schandelmeier, color (Box-folder 13/20)
      - With Schandelmeier and Jan Karski, color (Box-folder 13/21)
      - In studio with Ray C. Schandelmeier and pets, color. By Ray C. Schandelmeier (Box-folder 13/22)
      - With Rima Faber (Wolff). 8 x 10: 1990, in "Shopping cart" costume; polaroid: 1988 Nov. 6, birthday party for Dr. "Dub" Bullock at Edith Menard's and in Faber's studio, in Stillpoint costume, color (Box-folder 13/23)
      - Unidentified, 16 x 20, color (Box-folder 30/1)
    - Others (Box 14, Box 16, Box-folder 28/10-13, Box-folder 30/2)
      - Burkhardt, Beth and Denise Reed, 1986 July, color. National Zoo; choreographed by Burkhardt (Box-folder 16/81-82)
      - Caron, 14 x 11, 16 x 11 (Box-folder 29/2)
      - Carter, Tish, 1980 Dec., color (Box-folder 16/83)
      - Carter, Tish, color. Rocks; choreographed by Carter (Box-folder 16/84)
      - Departures: Dorothy Madden, Nicole Pearson, Rona Sande, and Beth Osgood Chanock, 1959 Dec. (Box-folder 14/1)
      - Encounters and goodbyes: Rima Faber, Sue Hannen; 1983; color. By Fred Underwood [?] (Box-folder 16/85-96)
      - Dirge, 1981, 1988 Jan. 27, color. Prints and contact sheets (Box-folder 14/2)
      - Faber (Wolff), Rima, 1980 Dec., color (Box-folder 16/97)
      - Galeota, Nancy, 1980 Dec., color (Box-folder 16/98)
      - Gieger, Esther, color (Box-folder 16/99)
      - Hannen, Sue, 1980 Dec., 1988 Jan. 27, 30, color. Prints and contact sheets (Box-folder 14/3)
      - Hannen, Sue, Stephanie Simmons, and Ellis, color. Jan Tievsky on far left (Box-folder 16/100-101)
      - Humphrey, Doris and Charles Weidman, 1935. New dance; on front: A merry Xmas from [signed] Charles (Box-folder 14/4)
      - Karski, Jan. By the Detroit News; on back: To my beloved Pola [signed] Jan (Box-folder 14/5)
      - Karski, Jan and Nancy Schandelmeier, color (Box-folder 14/6)
      - Karski, Jan and Ray C. Schandelmeier, color (Box-folder 14/7)
      - Koehler, Cheryl, 1980 Dec., color (Box-folder 16/102)
      - Knox, Marion, three 14 x 11, 13-3/4 x 10-1/2 (Box-folder 14/8, 29/3)
      - Kreutzberg, Harald (Box-folder 14/9)
      - Lerman, Liz, 1985 Jan., color. At a rehearsal of Russia: the transparent apple and the silver saucer, "Snow in Siberia" (Box-folder 16/103)
      - Lerman, Liz, 1987 April, color (Box-folder 16/104)
      - Life, 1983, color. By Fred Underwood [?] (Box-folder 16/105-111)
      - Nirenska, Mr. and Mrs. [Pola Nirenska's parents] (Box-folder 14/27)
      - Norman, 13 x 18, 16 x 20, 1968 Fall (Box-folder 30/2)
      - Osgood Chanock, Beth, Nicole Pearson, and Rona Sande, 1960s (Box-folder 14/10)
      - Osgood Chanock, Beth, Nicole Pearson, and Rona Sande, 11-1/4 x 10-1/4, 1960s (Box-folder 28/10)
      - Out of sorts: Sue Hannen, 1988 Jan. 27, color. Prints and contact sheets (Box-folder 14/11)
      - Pearson, Nicole, 1959 Dec., 1960 Oct. 6. By Naltchayan [1960] (Box-folder 14/12)
      - Pearson, Nicole, and Rona Sande, 1959 Dec. (Box-folder 16/112)
      - Reynolds, Greg. Print and contact sheet (Box-folder 14/13)
      - Russia: the transparent apple and the silver saucer, "Snow in Siberia": Liz Lerman, 1985 Jan., color (Box-folder 16/113-115)
      - Sande, Rona, 13-3/4 x 11, 1960s (Box-folder 29/4)
      - Schandelmeier family and friends, color. Prints and contact sheet (Box-folder 14/14)
      - Schandelmeier, Laura, color and b&w. Trilogy and other works; by Robert Yohn and Ray C. Schandelmeier (Box-folder 14/15)
      - Schandelmeier, Nancy, color (Box-folder 14/16)
      - Schandelmeier, Ray C., color. Prints and contact sheets (Box-folder 14/17)
      - Shout: Sharon Wyrrick, 1987 June, color (Box-folder 16/116-122)
      - Stillpoint: Rima Faber, 1990 (Box-folder 14/18)
      - Tate, Carolyn, 10-1/2 x 13-1/2, 1960s (Box-folder 28/11)
      - Tievsky, Jan, 1980 Dec., color (Box-folder 16/123)
      - Tievsky, Jan, color (Box-folder 16/124)
      - Topolski, Felix, color (Box-folder 14/19)
      - The train, 1990. By Michael Drago (Box-folder 14/20)
      - The train: Paula Camilli, Heather Doerbecker, Jan Taylor, and Jan [?], 8 x 12, 1990 (Box-folder 28/12)
      - Trip: Cathy Paine, 1982 Aug., color (Box-folder 16/125-132)
      - Web: Shawn Womack, 1987 Oct., color (Box-folder 16/133-142)
      - Wigman, Mary. By Ted Hurter, Zürich and Atelier Robertson, Berlin; autographed by Wigman (Box-folder 14/21)
      - Wigman, Mary, Elisabeth Wigman, and Hanya Holm (Box-folder 14/22)
      - Wilcox, Carrie, color (Box-folder 16/143)
      - Womack, Shawn, color (Box-folder 14/23)
      - Woman, first movement: Sharon Wyrrick, 1987 April, color (Box-folder 16/144-146)
      - Woman, second movement: Sharon Wyrrick, 1987 April, color (Box-folder 16/147-152)
      - Wyrrick, Sharon (Box-folder 14/24)
      - Unidentified: dancers, color and b&w. By Joel S. Hauserman (Box-folder 14/25)
      - Unidentified: friends and family, color and b&w (Box-folder 14/26)
      - 12 x 10 by John Deakin; autographed (Box-folder 28/13)
      - Unidentified: dance rehearsal, 1988 Nov., color (Box-folder 16/153-163)
    - By Nirenska (Box 15, Box 28-30)
      - A boy on the farm, 10-1/2 x 13-3/4, 1969. Print of the year, National Photographic Society (Box-folder 28/14)
      - Castle in Spain, 19-1/2 x 14, 1969 (Box-folder 30/3)
      - Delicate, 10-3/4 x 13-1/4 (Box-folder 28/15)
      - Dreaming, 11 x 14 (Box-folder 28/16)
      - Horizontal, 1968 (Box-folder 15/1)
      - I am mad, 14 x 17 (Box-folder 30/4)
      - July 4 (Box-folder 15/2)
      - Junior, 14-3/4 x 20 (Box-folder 30/5)
      - Landscapes, 8-1/4 x 13, 11 x 14-3/4, 11 x 14 (Box-folder 15/3, 28/17)
      - Listening, 11 x 14, 14 x 11 (Box-folder 29/5)
      - Marching band, 14 x 11 (Box-folder 29/6)
      - My spanish skirt, 1968 April. Accepted in the spring competition of the Greater Washington Council of Camera Clubs (Box-folder 15/4)
      - Nature's form, 16 x 20, 1968 (Box-folder 30/6)
      - Pets, 1968 Fall, b&w and color (Box-folder 15/5, 30/7)
      - Portrait of a farmer, 12-1/4 x 14-1/2, 1969 Jan. Honorable mention in portraits, Arts Club of Washington Pictorial Photography Annual Salon (Box-folder 29/7)
      - Portraits, two 11 x 14, two 14 x 11, 11 x 13-1/2, 13-1/4 x 10, three 20 x 16 (Box-folder 15/6, 29/8, 30/8)
      - Portraits of a child, 1967. Printed in Baby Talk in 1967 and 1968; copy of 1968 Christmas issue included (Box-folder 15/7)
      - Puff, 14 x 15-1/4, 1969 Jan. Print of the year, second place, National Photographic Society; displayed in Arts Club of Washington Pictorial Photography Annual Salon (Box-folder 30/9)
      - Still-life, two 11 x 14, 14 x 11, 11 x 14-3/4, two 16 x 20, color and b&w (Box-folder 15/8, 29/9, 30/10)
      - Study, two 16 x 20, 1968 (Box-folder 30/11)
      - Sulking (Box-folder 15/9)
      - Sulking, 12 x 10-3/4 (Box-folder 28/18)
      - Travel, 1987 Oct., color (Box-folder 16/164)
      - Village, 11 x 14, 16 x 20, 1968 (Box-folder 30/12)
      - Yawn, 11 x 14, 1967 Dec. Honorable mention, National Photographic Society (Box-folder 28/19)
      - Young painter, 17-1/2 x 15 (Box-folder 30/13)
      - Miscellaneous subjects, contact sheets (Box-folder 15/10)
    - By David Hasamatsu (Box-folder 28/20)
      - Winter scenes, 13-1/2 x 10, 13-1/2 x 10-3/4. Autographed (Box-folder 28/20)
    - Albums (Box 15-18)
      - St. Martin, 1977; 1980 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 16/165-166)
      - St. Martin, 1978 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 15/11)
      - St. Martin, 1978 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 16/167-171)
      - New York, 1978 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 16/172-174)
      - Guatemala, 1979 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 17/1-3)
      - 1979, spring-summer [color and b&w] (Box-folder 17/4-5)
      - Hungary, 1980 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 17/6-7)
      - New York, 1980 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 17/8)
      - Pets, 1979-80 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 17/9-10)
      - 1980-85 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 15/12)
      - 1980-85 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 17/11-15)
      - 1981-82 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 18/1-18)
      - 1982 July-Aug. [color and b&w] (Box-folder 18/19-21)
      - Japan, 1984 June [color and b&w] (Box-folder 15/13)
      - Japan, 1984 June [color and b&w] (Box-folder 18/22-24)
      - 1986-88 [color and b&w] (Box-folder 18/25-28)
  - Negatives (Box-folder 15, Box-folder 18, Box-folder 19-21)
    - Nirenska alone (Box-folder 15/14-17)
      - Eastern ballad, 8 x 10 copy negative, safety film (Box-folder 15/14)
      - Polish dance, 8 x 10 copy negative, safety film (Box-folder 15/15)
      - La puerta del vino, 8 x 10 copy negative, safety film (Box-folder 15/16)
      - A scarecrow remembers, 8 x 10 copy negatives, safety film (Box-folder 15/17)
    - Others (Box 19, Box-folder 18/29-31)
      - Burkhardt, Beth and Denise Reed, 1986 July, color. National Zoo; choreography by Burkhardt (Box-folder 19/1)
      - Dick (Box-folder 19/2-3)
      - Karski, Jan, color and b&w (Box-folder 19/4-23)
      - Knox, Marion (Box-folder 19/24-33)
      - Norman (Box-folder 19/34-47)
      - Osgood Chanock, Beth (Box-folder 19/38-41)
      - Payne (Nolan), Arvilla (Box-folder 19/42-51)
      - Pearson, Nicole, 5 x 4, 1964 Jan. 18. In The Evening Star (Box-folder 18/29)
      - Sande, Rona (Box-folder 19/52-64)
      - Students of Nirenska (Box-folder 19/65-101)
      - Thimey, Erika, with her sister, Herta (Box-folder 19/102-106)
      - The train: Paula Camilli, Heather Doerbecker, Jan Taylor, and Jan [?], 8 x 12, 1990 (Box-folder 19/107-114)
      - Xstery [?], Andrea (Box-folder 19/115-132)
      - Unidentified relatives, 3-3/4 x 2-3/4 copy negatives, safety film (Box-folder 18/30-31)
      - Unidentified (Box-folder 19/133-150)
    - By Nirenska (Box 20, Box 21, Box-folder 19/151-185)
      - Animals (Box-folder 19/151-153)
      - Genre (Box-folder 19/154-185)
      - Miscellaneous subjects, color and b&w (Box-folder 20/1-53)
      - Pets (Box-folder 20/54-64)
      - Photo class (Box-folder 20/65-67)
      - Portraits, three 16 mm. images, color and b&w (Box-folder 20/68-146)
      - Scapes: landscapes, seascapes, and cityscapes (Box-folder 21/1-64)
      - Spain (Box-folder 21/65-85)
      - Still-life, color and b&w (Box-folder 21/86-112)
      - Travel, color (Box-folder 21/113-137)
  - Slides by Nirenska (Box-folder 15/18)
    - Dusk [color] (Box-folder 15/18)
    - Landscapes [color]
    - Life begins [color]
    - Lonely bird [color]
    - Portraits [color]
    - Seascapes [color]
    - Still-life [color]
    - Unidentified [color]
- Art Work (Box 22, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30)
  The Art Work series is represented by two subseries: Costume designs and Drawings & paintings. The Costume designs subseries consists of drawings and paintings, primarily from the 1930s. The Drawings & paintings subseries consists of drawings and watercolors of Nirenska and colleagues, and several miscellaneous drawings and prints.
  Arranged alphabetically by type, title, and subject.
  - Costume designs (Box 22, Box 28, Box 30)
    - By Audrey Cruddas, annotated (Box-folder 28/21)
    - By Doroty Szenfeld, 1934 (Box-folder 22/1)
    - By Doroty Szenfeld, 1936 (Box-folder 22/2)
    - Costume, green and yellow (Box-folder 29/10)
    - Costume, Polish (Box-folder 28/22)
    - A scarecrow remembers, by Audrey Cruddas, annotated (Box-folder 30/14)
    - Unidentified (Box-folder 22/3)
  - Drawings and paintings (Box 22, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30)
    - Barnes commons, pencil drawing, by S. R. [?] (Box-folder 28/23)
    - La dame a l'éventail, by Pablo Picasso, print (Box-folder 29/11)
    - Drawings and watercolors, by A. H. C. [formerly Audrey Cruddas?] (Box-folder 29/12-14, 30/15)
    - Mardi Gras, by Paul Cézanne, print (Box-folder 29/15)
    - Nirenska, drawing, by Felix Topolski. Used for programs and as a bookplate; see also Subject Files, Pola Nirenska Dance Company (Box-folder 22/4)
    - Painting, by R. Mizufune, 1962 (Box-folder 22/5)
    - Pearson, Nicole and Rona Sande [?], watercolor, 1960s (Box-folder 29/16)
    - Pencil drawing, by Zardenberg [?] (Box-folder 30/16)
    - Sally, drawing, by Frances T. Trammell, 1964 (Box-folder 30/17)
    - Two bridges, by Sir Stanley Spencer, print (Box-folder 22/6)
    - Le vieux juif, by Pablo Picasso, print (Box-folder 29/17)
- Music (Box-folder 22/7-8)
  The Music series consists of autographed miniature score of Priaulx Rainier's Quartet for strings, printed score of the Polish national hymn.
  Arranged alphabetically by composer
  - Anonymous, Jeszcze Polska nie zginela (The Polish national hymn). Words by Josef Wybicki (Box-folder 22/7)
  - Rainier, Priaulx, Quartet for strings. Miniature score; autographed "For Pola from Priaulx 1942-1947" (Box-folder 22/8)
- Poetry, 1934-1936, 1949, 1987, undated (Box-folder 22/9-21)
  The Poetry series consists of poems for, about, and by Nirenska, a few miscellaneous others.
  Arranged alphabetically by author
  - Bymme; "On first seeing Pola" (Box-folder 22/9)
  - Faber Wolff, Rima; "Thanksgiving poems" (Box-folder 22/10)
  - Genega, Paul; "The courier"; 1987. For Jan Karski; original in correspondence, "G" miscellaneous (Box-folder 22/11)
  - Kraft, Marcy; Night flowers. To Nirenska with thanks for her inspiration (Box-folder 22/12)
  - Kraft, Marcy; "17 poems" (Box-folder 22/13)
  - Nirenska, Pola; "Dreamscape" (Box-folder 22/14)
  - Scheider, Hanns; "Sü-schy tanzt"; 1934 June 28 (Box-folder 22/15)
  - Seidl, Ina; "Aus der engelsuite, getanzt von Pola Nirenska (Versuch einer Bewegungsdeutung)" (Box-folder 22/16)
  - Seidl, Ina; "Der Schrei: Choreographische studie, getanzt v. Pola Nirenska, Warschau, anlässlich des Internat. Tanzwettbewerbes in Wien" (Box-folder 22/17)
  - Seidl, Ina; "Trance [and] Engel des todes"; Winter 1935-36. Based on Nirenska's choreography (Box-folder 22/18)
  - Seidl, R. [Ina ?]; "Erinnerungen einer Vogelscheuche, Studie über einen Tanz von Pola Nirenska"; 1949. Original in correspondence (Box-folder 22/19)
  - Winczakiewicz, Jan; Izrael w poezji Polskiej antologia (Box-folder 22/20)
  - Unidentified (Box-folder 22/21)
- Subject Files, 1933-1982 (Box 23)